Guide to the Gay & Lesbian Advocates & Defenders Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Gay & Lesbian Advocates & Defenders records
1973-2016
MS 1961
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
71.58
(175 boxes)
The records document the organization and activities of the Gay & Lesbian Advocates & Defenders (GLAD), a nonprofit legal organization dedicated to defending the rights of lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender individuals and people with HIV, primarily in New England. The collection primarily consists of correspondence, topical files, reports, meeting minutes, legal research, litigation and amicus files, publications, volunteer and training manuals, and newspaper clippings created or maintained by GLAD. The records document all aspects of the organization, including its history, structure, and activities from its founding in 1978 to the present. The collection provides a rich resource for the study of GLAD, anti-discrimination efforts, and the legal issues facing lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender people and people with HIV in the United States.
Gay and Lesbian Advocates and Defenders
Biographical / Historical
Gay & Lesbian Advocates & Defenders (GLAD), located in Boston, Massachusetts, was founded in 1978 by attorney John Ward and a group of New England lawyers and activists. Ward founded GLAD in response to the Boston Police Department's entrapment of over 100 gay patrons in the Boston Public Library. The event would become the foundation of GLAD's first case, Doe v. McNiff.
Best known for its litigation of the Massachusetts case Goodridge v. Dept. of Public Health, which established for the first time the right of same-sex couples to marry, GLAD was one of the first legal organizations in the United States dedicated solely to defending the rights of gay men and lesbians. Originally established to fight attacks and discrimination against the gay, lesbian and bisexual community, GLAD has, over time, expanded its mission to include transgender people and people with HIV. In 1985, GLAD launched the AIDS Law Project with the purpose of fighting AIDS-related discrimination, and in the early 1990s, it established the Civil Rights Project to focus on civil rights issues in the gay and lesbian community. GLAD rewrote its mission statement in 2000 to include the eradication of discrimination based on "gender identity and expression," in addition to "sexual orientation and HIV status," which led to the formal creation of the Transgender Rights Project in 2008. GLAD has also been committed to educating the lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender community, the legal community, and the general public about the legal and civil rights of lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender people, and of people with HIV.
Located in Boston since its inception, GLAD has primarily served the six New England states: Connecticut, Maine, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, Rhode Island and Vermont. It divides its work into three major functions: Legal, Public Affairs & Education, and Development. The Legal department handles litigation and other legal matters and does most of GLAD's legislative work. The Public Affairs & Education department fulfills GLAD's mission to educate the public, while the Development department is responsible for generating funds to maintain and grow GLAD's operations, which are primarily supported by donations.
Although GLAD is a thriving and influential organization, its establishment as a small organization run by volunteers has heavily influenced its administrative history. The organization is governed by a board of directors and run by an executive director, who is responsible for day-to-day operations. John Ward served as its first executive director until 1983. In that year, Kathy Travers became the second executive director of GLAD and its first full-time, paid employee. In 1984, attorney Kevin Cathcart took over the position, which he held for eight years. Throughout the 1980s, GLAD's staff remained small, and the executive director was responsible for all of GLAD's operations. GLAD relied on its relationships with outside attorneys to handle many of its cases. The office manager position became a full-time paid position in 1986, around the same time that GLAD hired its first staff attorney, Denise McWilliams, to direct the AIDS Law Project. The hiring of McWilliams increased the size of the full-time staff to three. By 1990, the full-time staff had grown to five with the addition of a development director in 1988 and another staff attorney, Mary Bonauto, in 1990. During the 1990s, GLAD continued to grow and had several executive directors: Josephine Ross (1992-1993), Jan Platner (1993-1995), Amelia Craig (1995-1997), and Gary Buseck (1997-2003). In times when the position was left vacant, GLAD staff attorneys Denise McWilliams (in 1992), Mary Bonauto (in 1995), and Bennett Klein (in 1997) stepped in as acting executive director. In 2005, Lee Swislow became the executive director. By 2010 GLAD had a staff of thirty, including eight attorneys, two distinct departments serving GLAD's development and public affairs/education needs, and a budget of $3.1 million.
Some of GLAD's notable cases include Doe v. McNiff (1978); Babets v. Johnston (1985), which addressed the right of same-sex couples to become foster parents; Bragdon v. Abbott (1995), which established that people living with HIV/AIDS are protected under the Federal Americans with Disabilities Act; Rosa v. Park West Bank (2000) and Doe v. Yunits (2000), both of which affirmed the right of transgender people to legal protection against discrimination; Baker v. Vermont (1999), which led to the creation of civil unions in Vermont; and Goodridge v. Dept. of Public Health (2003) and Kerrigan & Mock v. Dept. of Public Health (2008), which together established same-sex marriage in their respective states of Massachusetts and Connecticut.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Gay & Lesbian Advocates and Defenders, 2010, 2014, and 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Arrangement
The records are organized in five series: I. Administration, 1975-2006. II. Legal, 1990-2008. III. Public Affairs & Education, 1976-2010. IV. Development, 1982-2003. V. Non-GLAD Publications, 1973-2006; and three additions.
Scope and Contents
The records document the organization and activities of the Gay & Lesbian Advocates & Defenders (GLAD), a nonprofit legal organization dedicated to defending the rights of lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender individuals and people with HIV, primarily in New England. The collection primarily consists of correspondence, topical files, reports, meeting minutes, legal research, litigation and amicus files, publications, volunteer and training manuals, and news clippings created or maintained by GLAD. The records document all aspects of the organization, including its history, structure, and activities from its founding in 1978 to the present. The collection provides a rich resource for the study of GLAD, anti-discrimination efforts, and the legal issues facing lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender people and people with HIV in the United States.
Material on GLAD's founding and history are found in the collection, as is material related to the administration of the organization. The Board of Directors and Executive Director files include committee reports, a complete set of meeting minutes and packets, correspondence, and topical files providing a rich overview of GLAD's activities. Financial records consist of auditor, public charity, and general budget reports, which provide information about GLAD's financial status and growth over the years. Legal files consist of reports and litigation and amicus files, documenting only a few of the cases in which GLAD was involved. The Public Affairs files provide substantive information which can be used to reconstruct GLAD's history and more generally the history of the legal status of lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender individuals and people with HIV in the United States. Of particular note are GLAD's publications and the news clippings they maintained. The Education files include documentation on GLAD's educational and outreach missions, including its Lawyer Referral Service, InfoLine (a phone based guidance and referral service), forums, and presentations. The Development files document fundraising. In addition to the records generated by GLAD, the collection includes a substantial number of newsletters, flyers, and brochures (Non-GLAD Publications) of various local and national lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender organizations (usually only a few items per organization). While not comprehensive, the non-GLAD publications provide a glimpse of the lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender activist milieu primarily from the 1980s and 1990s.
AIDS (Disease) -- Law and legislation -- United States; Bisexuals -- United States; Civil rights; Gay men -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Gay rights -- United States; HIV-positive persons -- Civil rights -- United States; HIV-positive persons -- Law and legislation -- United States; Homosexuality -- Law and legislation -- United States; Homosexuality; Lesbians -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Lesbians -- United States; Same-sex marriage; Sex discrimination -- United States; Transgender people -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Transsexuals -- United States; LGBTQ resource; Gay and Lesbian Advocates and Defenders
- Administration, 1975-2006; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of records documenting GLAD's administration. It is divided into four sections: Board of Directors; Executive Director; Finance; and Office Administration. The board records consist primarily of minutes, committee records and "packets" which contain documents provided to the board summarizing the work of GLAD's various committees and departments. The packets provide an overview of various administrative, legal, financial, outreach and organizational matters before GLAD at any given moment. Executive Director files contain correspondence, topical files, notes, memoranda, articles, and reports. The early records of the executive director contain documentation and information that would later (circa 1990) be filed under Development and Public Affairs & Education.
  - Board
    - Committees
      - Administration and Finance, 1995 June-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1-12)
      - Development, 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13-21)
      - Executive Director Search, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Litigation, 1983-1995 (Box 1, Folder 23-27)
      - Operating, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
      - Outreach/Education, 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
      - Strategic Planning, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - Meetings (minutes and packets)
      - 1978-1986 (Box 2, Folder 11-19)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
      - 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 1-8)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
      - 1992-1993 April (Box 6, Folder 1-13)
      - 1993 May-1994 (Box 7, Folder 1-19)
      - 1995 (Box 8, Folder 1-10)
      - 1996 January-October (Box 9, Folder 1-10)
      - 1996 November-1997 October (Box 10, Folder 1-13)
      - 1997 November-1998 (Box 11, Folder 1-15)
      - 1999-2001 (Box 12, Folder 1-30)
      - 2002 January-November (Box 13, Folder 1-9)
    - Membership
      - Lists, Circa 1984-1993 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Policy, 1978-1993 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Executive Director
    Arrangement
    Arranged chronologically by tenure of executive director.
    - Ward, John
      - Correspondence, 1978-1982 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - NEFIR (National Education Foundation for Individual Rights), 1979-1983 (Box 13, Folder 13-16)
    - Travers, Kathy
      - Adoption, Undated (Box 13, Folder 17)
      - Annual meetings and reports, 1978-1983 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      - Anti-Discrimination ordinance, 1980-1982 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
      - Bar, Undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Case cites, Circa 1982 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Commonwealth Bank and Trust, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Criminal prosecution, Undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Criminal records and sealing, privacy of, Circa 1982 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Cross-dressing (transvestism), 1975-1979 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Depo-Provera/ACLU Prison Project, 1981-1983 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Fundraising/Grants, 1979-1984 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - Gay prisoners, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - Income reports, budgets, etc., 1982-1984 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      - Legislation: ordinances and statutes prohibiting discrimination, 1982-1984 (Box 14, Folder 13)
      - Lesbians, general articles, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 14)
      - Liquor licensing cases, Circa 1981 (Box 14, Folder 15)
      - Marriage, Boston Phoenix article, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 16)
      - Military, 1982-1984 (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
      - NEFIR (National Education Foundation for Individual Rights), 1981-1983 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - NEFIR/Lambda conference calls, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - News articles on legal issues, 1983-1984 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Revolt, 1981 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - Sex and gender, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - Sodomy statistics, 1981-1983 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Solicitation-- People v. Joseph /California, 1981 (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Spousal privilege/immunity, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - Transsexuals, 1975-1976 (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - Uplinger-- State of New York v. Robert Uplinger, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 12)
      - Urvashi, 1981-1983 (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - Welfare, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Cathcart, Kevin
      - AIDS, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - AIDS Law Project (ALP) information, Undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - AIDS Law Project paralegal job description, 1990-1991 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), 1984-1986 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Annual reports and GLAD Briefs, 1982-1987 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Anti-gay violence, 1984-1988 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Anti-porn ordinance articles, 1984-1985 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Art Alliance, 1983-1984 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - Audit - 1990 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - Bangor, Maine, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Banks, Robert (Judge), 1985 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Board of Directors
        - Description, information, etc., 1987-1992 (Box 16, Folder 12)
        - Loans, 1984-1985 (Box 16, Folder 13)
        - Search, 1989-1991 (Box 16, Folder 14-17)
      - Boards, organization information, 1982-1983 (Box 16, Folder 18)
      - Bork (Judge Robert Bork), 1987 (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - Boston College, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 20)
      - Boston Jacks, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 21)
      - Brochure, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 22)
      - Brookline school teachers, 1984-1985 (Box 16, Folder 23)
      - Buckley, Circa 1992 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Budget, 1984-1992 (Box 17, Folder 2-5)
      - Citizens Alliance for Gay and Lesbian Rights (CAGLR), 1986 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Civil Liberty Union of Massachusetts (CLUM), Massachusetts Civil Liberties Union Foundation (MCLUF), 1976-1992 (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Civil Rights Task Force, 1985-1989 (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - Client account instructions, Undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - Client confidentiality of alcohol and drug abuse patient records, Massachusetts Department of Health and Human Services, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - Clinical studies, articles, etc. (miscellaneous psychiatric information), 1982 (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Community Research Initiative of New England (CRINE) letter of support, 1989 (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - Conference Calls, Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund, 1984-1987 (Box 17, Folder 13-14)
      - Conferences
        - "Building a Multi-Cultural Community 2/15/90", 1990 (Box 17, Folder 15)
        - Gay Fathers Coalition, 1985 (Box 17, Folder 16)
        - Lesbian and Gay Families, Lambda, 1987 July (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Connecticut and Massachusetts Law on Quarantine, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence
        General
        See also: Letters, box 22, folders 1-4
        - General, 1986-1989 (Box 18, Folder 3-6)
        - French Wall, The Guide, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 7)
        - Requests for information, 1985-1988 (Box 18, Folder 8-10)
        - Sterling Stowell, 1987-1989 (Box 18, Folder 11-13)
      - Denise McWilliams
        - Information/speaking, 1989-1991 (Box 18, Folder 14)
        - Résumé, Circa 1986 (Box 18, Folder 15)
      - Department of Social Services, 1984-1985 (Box 18, Folder 16)
      - Development Director, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 17)
      - Dickey, B., 1985 (Box 18, Folder 18)
      - Discrimination - miscellaneous, 1980-1985 (Box 18, Folder 19)
      - Division of Public Charities, Massachusetts Department of the Attorney General, 1978-1981 (Box 18, Folder 20)
      - Divorce/separation agreement, laws, etc., 1984 (Box 18, Folder 21)
      - Docket Control System, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 22)
      - Domestic partners, insurance and benefits, 1982-1984 (Box 18, Folder 23)
      - Doonesbury cartoons, 1989 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - Equity Institute (Project Empowerment), 1987 (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - Executive director
        - Job search, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 3)
        - Reviews, 1989 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - Fair Housing Commission, 1984-1989 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Family law, 1989 (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - Federal employees, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - Felman, Jyl (development consultant), 1987 (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - Former board members, 1989 (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - Freedom of Information Act guide, 1990 (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - Fund for Human Dignity, 1987 (Box 19, Folder 11)
      - Fundraisers, Undated (Box 19, Folder 12)
      - Gay and Lesbian Activists, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 13)
      - Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), 1989-1991 (Box 19, Folder 14)
      - Gay and Lesbian Defense Committee, 1986 (Box 19, Folder 15)
      - Gay and Lesbian Parents Coalition International, 1982 (Box 19, Folder 16)
      - Gay rights law, bill and referendum, 1985-1990 (Box 19, Folder 17-18)
      - Gay Rights National Lobby and Leadership Forum, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Gentile, Mary, 1989 (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - Gingrade, Barbara, Undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - GLAD
        - Descriptive information, Undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
        - History, 1987 (Box 20, Folder 5)
        - Logos, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - GLCS (Gay and Lesbian Counseling Service), 1985 (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - Grand jury, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - Grantsmanship Center, 1984 (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - Greater Boston Business Council, 1991 (Box 20, Folder 10)
      - Greater Boston Civil Rights Coalition, 1989 (Box 20, Folder 11)
      - H-226 Bill (Denise McWilliams' letter), 1989 (Box 20, Folder 12)
      - Harvard Community Health Plan/Dentist, Circa 1985 (Box 20, Folder 13)
      - Hewitt, Emily, 1991 (Box 20, Folder 14)
      - Human Rights Campaign Fund, 1985-1987, 1991 (Box 20, Folder 15-16)
      - Human rights ordinance, San Francisco, 1984-1986 (Box 20, Folder 17)
      - Human rights ordinance and commission, Boston, 1984-1988 (Box 20, Folder 18)
      - Human rights ordinances (other cities and states), 1984-1987 (Box 20, Folder 19)
      - Immigration, 1983-1989 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Immigration Reform and Control Act, 1986 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Intake forms, blank, Undated (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - International Gay and Lesbian Human Rights Commission, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - International Lesbian and Gay Association, 1982 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - Job descriptions
        - GLAD, 1984-1988 (Box 21, Folder 6)
        - Non-GLAD, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 7)
        - Other, 1989-1990 (Box 21, Folder 8)
      - Kevin Cathcart
        - Biographical information, Undated (Box 21, Folder 9)
        - Departure, 1992 (Box 21, Folder 10)
      - Kowalski, Sharon, information, 1988-1989 (Box 21, Folder 11)
      - Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund, 1984-1992 (Box 21, Folder 12-13)
      - Lavin, Lewis, 1991 (Box 21, Folder 14)
      - Lawyers for Human Rights, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 15)
      - Legislative directory, 1985-1987 (Box 21, Folder 16)
      - Letters
        See also: Correspondence, box 18, folders 3-13
        - and publications, 1992 (Box 22, Folder 1)
        - Fringe, 1990-1991 (Box 22, Folder 2)
        - Miscellaneous, 1987-1991 (Box 22, Folder 3)
        - To the editor, 1984-1990 (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - Mailings, 1987 (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - Maine, 1985-1991 (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - March on Washington - 1987, 1993, 1987-1992 (Box 22, Folder 7-8)
      - Mary Bonauto information / speaking, 1990-1991 (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - Maryland, Baltimore, Non-Discrimination Ordinance, 1984 (Box 22, Folder 10)
      - Massachusetts Commission Against Discrimination, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 11)
      - Massachusetts Gay and Lesbian Political Caucus, 1987-1990 (Box 22, Folder 12)
      - Massachusetts Lesbian and Gay Bar Association, 1985-1991 (Box 22, Folder 13)
      - Massachusetts Tenants Organization, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 14)
      - Metropolitan District Commission / Fenway violence, 1988 (Box 22, Folder 15)
      - Middlesex County Civil Rights Advisory Council, 1987 (Box 22, Folder 16)
      - Military/Draft, 1985-1989 (Box 22, Folder 17)
      - Names Project, 1991 (Box 22, Folder 18)
      - National Center for Lesbian Rights, 1991-1992 (Box 22, Folder 19)
      - National Coming Out Day, 1988, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 20-21)
      - National Day of Mourning, 1989 (Box 22, Folder 22)
      - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force, 1984-1992 (Box 22, Folder 23-24)
      - National Gay Rights Advocates, 1989 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - National Lawyers Guild, 1985-1991 (Box 23, Folder 2-3)
      - National Lesbian and Gay Law Association, 1990-1991 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - National Lesbian and Gay Law Students, 1988 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - New England Advisory Committee, 1985-1987 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - New Hampshire, 1984-1991 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - O'Donnell, Steven, 1990 (Box 23, Folder 8)
      - Organizations (miscellaneous), 1987-1989 (Box 23, Folder 9)
      - Personnel policy, 1986 (Box 23, Folder 10)
      - Police practices, 1992 (Box 23, Folder 11)
      - Press, GLAD people in the news, 1989-1991 (Box 23, Folder 12)
      - Prisoners, 1984-1986 (Box 23, Folder 13)
      - Privacy issues, 1986-1987 (Box 23, Folder 14)
      - Privacy Project (NGLTF), 1987 (Box 23, Folder 15)
      - Professional Liability Insurance, 1992 (Box 23, Folder 16)
      - Project Empowerment, 1987 (Box 23, Folder 17)
      - Quakers, 1987 (Box 23, Folder 18)
      - Rehabilitation Act of 1973, 1986 (Box 23, Folder 19)
      - Resources, Boston area, 1987 (Box 23, Folder 20)
      - Rhode Island, 1984-1986 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - Right wing homophobes, 1984-1985 (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - Roundtable, National Lesbian and Gay Civil Rights, 1987-1990 (Box 24, Folder 3)
      - Schools/Colleges, 1985-1990 (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - Security clearances, 1984-1987 (Box 24, Folder 5)
      - Shapiro, Jan, Circa 1991 (Box 24, Folder 6)
      - Social Law Library, 1990-1993 (Box 24, Folder 7)